hello
today i chat with carl fristen who is a
computational neuroscientist one of the
most cited researchers of all time
and we chat about his free energy
principle which is
has been likened to natural selection as
these deeply fundamental
principles and ideas to understand how
reality works and how it evolves
so
at carl is this amazing polymath and we
go all the way from the big bang through
to the future of artificial intelligence
and so i hope you
listen and check out this episode in
order to understand a deeply fundamental
principle the free energy principle
for how life
works and how to kind of see the matrix
for what is actually
occurring in reality okay thanks and
enjoy
[Music]
hello listeners my name is reese
lindmark i'm the founder of root and
welcome to the reshow
i believe this century is a turning
point in human history and i'm here to
help you navigate it to do so we'll
demystify the hidden but crucial ideas
that you can't find anywhere else and by
understanding these transformational
changes in science technology and
society and how to apply those ideas to
your daily life i hope to turn you into
an active participant in collectively
building our solar punk future so with
that in mind today i'm excited to chat
with carl fristen carl is a theoretical
neuroscientist and a professor at
university college london he's this
amazing polymath who is one of the most
sighted researchers of all time carl
thanks for being on the show and welcome
it's a great pleasure to be here
yeah we're excited to dive in and and
i've essentially been free energy
principal pilled
in the last kind of week or so um i've
had folks we've had folks on the podcast
like andy clark before talking about
predictive processing but now
i've kind of taken it one step further
and fallen further down the rabbit hole
and understanding one of carl's crucial
ideas this kind of you know free energy
principle you've done a lot of work on
brains um and now you're kind of
you know this this idea the free energy
principle some people have described it
as the most crucial idea since darwin's
natural selection which is a high praise
so
with that as kind of a background and
before i kind of give an overview on on
some other things we're going to chat
about could you just for our listeners
carl explain what is the free energy
principle what is active inference um
and how does it apply to our daily life
well if you've had andy on describing
predictive processing i think that's a
very nice entree into what
the free energy principle is about it
it's essentially
a
an attempt
to provide a method or a principle of
the kind that you would find in physics
that would be fit for purpose to
understand and explain sentient behavior
and of course the kind of scented
behavior we're talking about is exactly
what andy was talking about in terms of
the predictive brain
the brain as a
a statistical organ that's predicting
trying to make sense of its data and
then planning and choosing the best way
then to go and secure some more data
so that's the agenda it's essentially to
understand ourselves and how we make
sense of our sensations but to do so in
a way you can write it down in terms of
equations and you can put them to a
computer with the agenda then
assimilating this kind of sentience and
building little artifacts and trying to
understand broken brains
make
more efficient computing devices
but of course to do that you really have
to become an engineer and a physicist do
you know to understand the basic
fundamentals so that's the agenda um i
could go on and explain the technical
foundations of it but perhaps we should
save that for your more probing
questions later on exactly that's great
yeah and i think um as and this is a
beautiful part of of carl's work is that
and i you know they just released carl
along with two other co-authors just
released this book on active inference
and um a week ago and so i kind of sped
read it over the weekend and it is um
it's good but it's it's got those
formalisms the mathematics in it so it's
kind of cool to hear these kind of
crucial ideas that do apply for
everything but are like connected to
formal mathematics that you could
actually simulate and code up in a
computer
so
with that said let me let me kind of um
give you and and our listener some
context here for for why i want to touch
on the free energy principle and you
talked about it in this crucial way is
this like understanding of sentient
behavior and so
you know for me right now i'm writing
this book on what information wants
which looks at how genes kind of created
the tree of life and how memes created
this tree of ideas
and the free energy principle
is
you know you know so so my book takes
this i kind of big history perspective
um on understanding kind of sentient
behavior and kind of how these ideas
replicate and things like that and so
i want to kind of
look at you know understanding the free
energy principles kind of like touching
it from the blind men touching the
elephant where you're like what does it
look like from this perspective in this
perspective and so we're going to take
maybe five perspectives today to kind of
look at it the first is this kind of
information
how information flowed in the universe
before replicators before genes and
memes
and we'll look at like whether the free
energy principle applies to the sun for
example and then we'll kind of go into
life and biology and genes and looking
at how the free energy principle applies
to like the pre-brain organisms like in
rna soup well you know what was the free
energy principle doing there and then
finally you know with memes thinking
about both the brain and you know what
the free energy principle has to say
about the kinds of information that can
live in our minds and then also more
generally about human society is
something like you know these weird like
myths that we you know organize around
like christianity does that apply or
abide by the free energy principle and
then finally finally we'll look at
machine learning and ai and kind of the
combination between free energy
principle and um and that so that's kind
of what we're gonna do
to give you an overview carl and with
that
let's start with the beginning here with
the information pre-replicators so
does the free energy principle it's an
understanding of sentient behavior does
something like the sun comply with it or
or how how does it the sun is stable but
it doesn't model the environment how do
you think about the free energy
principle pre-sentient life
right
so we're going to do everything aren't
we so we're starting at the beginning
which is excellent yeah
um so there is actually a deep
connection between um the sun and
replication um in the very simple sense
that the sun replicates its position
um
in the sense that it orbits you know
around its center whatever that is and
of course we orbit around the sun
so i use the words orbit or the word
orbit deliberately here because that's
something that's quite fundamental
to the kind of dynamics that we want to
understand
um
so
everything that exists
essentially has this aspect that it
keeps revisiting states that it has once
been in
so whether we're talking about the
orbits of heavenly bodies
uh or whether we're talking about the
beating of my heart or whether we're
talking about my annual cycle as i look
forward to easter my birthday and
christmas or whether talking about
biorhythms more generally right down to
the fast fluctuations and
electrochemical potentials in one neuron
in one part of my hippocampus at every
temporal scale at every level
we have this fundamental dynamic
where you keep coming back to where you
started not unlike a sort of strange
loop
so
this is something that is quite crucial
and possibly even definitional
of things that exist they re-keep their
states of being
within a limited set
so by definition they have to keep on
returning to a place in some abstract
state space that they once occupied
so the free energy principle is then
in the game of saying well if things
exist in the sense that they keep
returning to what's technically called
an attracting set of states for the sun
it's a very simple well for the earth
say it's a very simple
set of states it's just that your
positions on the orbit around
that it pursues
so
the fringy principle then is in the game
of trying to understand what dynamical
properties
must systems possess
if they have this
natural characteristic but also quite
remarkable characteristic that they
don't diverge exponentially they don't
dissipate they don't decay
they don't diffuse into nothing that
they keep themselves to within
restricted set of states if you like a
sort of generalized homeostasis
so everything that you want to know
about the free energy principle can
simply be derived
from saying well how must systems flow
what kind of dynamics do systems possess
if they also possess this this um these
attracting um these attracting sets or
these orbits if you like
um yeah now can i pause this for a
second actually sure
yeah yeah so that love that and i think
it's yeah it's super connected i've
heard some people describe the free
energy principle as you know if you
think about natural selection and
survival of the fittest but then you're
like oh wait it's actually a survival of
the stable you know so you have to have
these stable things and in order to be
stable then yeah you have um
you have to be orbiting around some kind
of um attractor set and i think you know
for me and trying to understand the free
energy principle that visual was so
crucial for me it's just thinking about
you know like ourselves as beings in
non-equilibrium steady states that are
kind of you know walking around
something you know for for a fish it's
good for the fish to be mostly in water
most of the time so it can't like go
crazy off somewhere else or like for me
i like being in cities and you know
taking showers and eating food or
whatever and so like i'm not just but
something like the sun
i think is is more difficult because
it's it's less of a non-equilibrium
steady state and it's also
the sun doesn't have a model of its
environment and i feel like the model of
its environment is a crucial part of
three injured principles so tell me how
the sun
does that you know
yep right well in fact the sun doesn't
probably um and there's a
so that's a really excellent question
that you also what differentiates
something that could be described i mean
clearly the sun's not inert but in the
sense of having an active role in the
way that it behaves it has a certain
inanimacy so i think there's a key
distinction between things that exist
that keep revisiting exist you know
pre-existing states that are animate and
inanimate and what you're asking is what
differentiates um their inanimate from
anime kinds
before i sort of drill down on that i
just wanted to pick up on the on the you
know
the lovely connections with evolution
and you know just using the word
replicator you know uh using the notion
of replication immediately talks about
this this sort of cyclical this
solenoidal
just a life cycle is another statement
of this fundamental
orbital nature so many people would
would actually say it is not it is not
survival
of
the fittest that is the best way to
understand evolution is just what things
persist for long periods of time so it
is that persistence that sort of
existence in perpetuity for extended
periods of time that has this sort of uh
stability and interestingly just one
final little thing and of course the
mathematics of what we are talking about
uh the the mathematical definition
of a non-equilibrium system or a far
from equilibrium system would require it
to have a solenoidal flow and what is
solenoidal flow and evolution well it's
red queen dynamics it's a sort of you
know say predator prey light
relationship again these continual
cycles where you have this your
itinerary that has this orbital orbital
aspect so your this dynamic is quite
fundamental at every level i'm sure
it'll it'll it'll appear also in terms
of memes that persist
at a different level now so let's come
back to this um key question
um of particular or natural kinds that
that do and do not have or look as if
they behave as if they have uh some
predictive capacity so they're doing
some predictive processing or they're
engaging in some kind of active
inference
i think the first thing to um
to say as well okay we've defined the
kind of system that um
that we want to talk about in that it
has orbits it has an itinerancy
and it occupies a small number of states
that it could occupy very much like the
officials being in water as opposed to
on the streets of new york
then um but we've got to do a little bit
more heavy lifting here a little bit
more work because you know as soon as
you talk about something you have to be
able to distinguish the states of the
thing you're talking about from the
states of everything else so you know
i have to be able to identify the states
of the earth the position of the earth
and the position of the states of the
sun for example i have to be able to
distinguish or disambiguate your states
from my states or my states from the
rest of the world
that introduces this notion of a markov
blanket which is central to the free
energy principle so on one reading you
can look at the free energy principle
just as a rehash of quantum mechanics
classical mechanics statistical
mechanics
they're all they all inherit from
exactly the same assumptions and with
one exception that the free energy
principle just puts a markov blanket
into the mix and that just enables you
to separate the states that are internal
to something relative to what's outside
and it's that sort of distinction which
brings the notion of prediction and
information into the game because now
you've got a distinction between the
inside and the outside where the inside
and outside states are separated by
blanket states at the surface of the sun
on the surface of a cell or your surface
or all your sensory and active states
and then you can now talk about the
inside
having beliefs of a mathematical
subpersonal sort or statistical um
correspondences
with the outside and you can now talk
in terms of information theory
about the inside
holding some information or having
information about the outside because
you've got this sort of
exchange across the markov blanket
i introduced the notion of a markov
planking because i have to do that in
order to answer your question about the
difference between um the sun and you um
the difference um technically it's just
the sun doesn't have what's called
active states it you know it doesn't
have any way
of its deep state so let's think about a
stone for example um as you know
something that certainly exists it's got
a uh it's got a mark off blanket or
blanket states the surface of the stone
you can separate the surface of the
stone from
everything else and it's got some deep
internal states but the key difference
between
me and the stone
is that my internal states express
themselves through the blanket they
express themselves
from the inside out and therefore you
can see me behave
in a way that looks as if i'm planning i
have um
you know
beliefs about what's going to happen to
me that i'm fulfilling um i'm acting in
a purposeful way and it may look indeed
as if i'm acting in a mindful way simply
because uh the my active states are now
um in a position
to affect the outside again
so one simple observation
that discriminates a stone from you
or a stone from any animate biotic
system
is that you move
you know
so he is as simple as that that you
can move in an autonomous way
whereas stones and planets they
certainly move but in a frame of
reference which is you know has no
autonomous aspect to it they you know
that
they don't change their shape they're
not shape-shifting in the same way that
we are and of course if we can move we
become animate and we can influence the
outside states external states
in a way
that makes them
more predictable basically and you know
i'm using that word because you can link
that now to andy's formulation you know
we are all predictive processing
machines
and of course if we're if we're good at
predictive processing we must be able to
engineer the kinds of environment that
deliver
sensory signals onto our markov blanket
that can be predicted and you can get
into all sorts of interesting um
arguments about niche construction or
just being um um
just uh
the raison d'etre for things like
language that we both share that makes
you and i mutually predictable and
that's how we work but because we
couldn't engage in that exchange and
leverage that predictability unless we
were able to talk and move so you won't
see the sun talking to you in in the
kind of way that where that we're
talking
i hope there may be a future in which
you know the sun gets it's you know the
that's the classic um
image of the sun being a like a smiling
thing and saying hi good morning you
know like we'll have to engineer that
into the sun rather than it being
natural so i think that your description
there makes sense and what i'm hearing
there just to reflect it is that yeah
that we have these active states that
allow us to move and allow us to model
and then kind of interact in the
environment and one way that i think
about it kind of and correct me if i'm
wrong here is like
there are kind of certain things that
can be stable and that can rotate around
either non-equilibrium or kind of
orbital states in the world
and and we label those things objects
like sun or a cat or a rock or humans
and and there are a lot of those things
that are kind of animate and
in order to be animate you have to go
through this weird like non-equilibrium
world and you're kind of you have to
have these active states in order to get
more energy in order to model the world
not just to dissipate
but then there's these kind of inanimate
ones
and those ones you can kind of think of
as like the laws of physics have allowed
for a certain set of things
to exist that are kind of you know the
sun just like i'm kind of fit with nice
construction you know like a like a fish
is fit for its environment
so too is the sun kind of fit with the
laws of physics in that it can be
there's a certain set of stable things
that can exist aka a bunch of hydrogen
atoms getting together you know
exploding making heat you know getting
in gravity there rotating around and
being a sun and that there's kind of a
certain kind of environmental niche that
exists that doesn't require active
states doesn't require modeling in the
environment but is just like an
inanimate thing that can exist based off
of the uh the laws of the physics is
that kind of what do you think about
that reflection
no i think that's a great picture um and
it's particularly um astute because it
speaks to this sort of separation of
scales both in space and in time and so
one way
that um some people including myself
think of things is that you you as you
go from the very very small from the
quantum to the um the very very big so
we're talking about sort of um you know
cosmology and sons and planets and the
like
then there is a
a natural progression from
very
random behavior
to much more precise behavior um and as
you get more and more precise and you
get bigger and bigger and bigger you
actually lose a degree of itinerancy
that characterizes you and me i mean we
are certainly um i you know
characterized by biorhythms and
all sorts of fluctuations but the kinds
of orbits that we enjoy
um are have an itinerancy they have a
sort of complexity which is not
characteristic of the orbit of the moon
for example and that may well simply be
um that very very big things
don't have the kind of uh itinerancy
that would associate with biotic systems
so it may well be that um
where things like us
are are certainly much much bigger than
the quantum scale because at the quantum
scale then random fluctuations would
effectively diffuse or um disperse or
mask any of this sort of solenoidal
orbital behavior
but we're small enough still to have
this kind of itinerancy
and we only have that eye tendency in
virtue of the fact we live in a nice
stable world where the moon goes around
the sun around the earth and the earth
goes around the sun everything uh
everything is sufficiently stable over
very long periods of time so you know
seeing things in that kind of context i
think is absolutely essential it is only
because
we have this slow predictable orbits of
the heavenly bodies
that are
changing the the context on the surface
of the earth
that provides a simple context in which
we can now
allow say evolutionary evolution can now
emerge
and that being a very slow dynamical
process that contextualizes
the evolution of phenotypes those
phenotypes now can learn and what do
they learn they learn how to predict and
they can predict uh all the way down to
you know
the the machinery you need to do that
prediction which is basically our brain
cells doing that so everything at the
finer scale rests upon
the right context established by the
slower
more persistent but still solenoidal
still uh orbiting uh scale above but of
course it's true the other way around
you know you
you you you don't get the emergence of
uh
of species or you don't get evolution
unless you have the right kind of
phenotype you don't have the right kind
of phenotype unless it's got the right
kind of brain you don't have the right
kind of brain unless you've got the
right kind of neuron so at every level
this this sort of itinerant orbiting
this um
persistence in terms of the the dynamics
that enable the system to retain or
remain in its attracting states depends
upon the scale at scale above so that's
a real i think a really really important
point
yeah the free energy principle cannot
apply any single level it has to
accommodate all of those levels
i love that i think i think i love that
and i love it as kind of like when
people talk about the goldilocks um
position for for earth it's like oh
we're like not too hot not too cold and
that's true but there's a more kind of
there's a goldilocks position of scale
and there's a goldilocks position of um
randomness versus stability you know and
so just like there's a lot of special
things that need to occur for us to be
able to have replicators that can can
like learn about the environment and the
environment's not being too crazy but
it's also not being too stable so yeah
that's that's really interesting let's
let's kind of take that and move into um
moving forward in time from you know the
big bang time to now um you know we're
starting to get life you know we're
starting to get um you know genes and
and biology how do you the first
question actually is how do you think
about
the free energy principle there's an
abstract question but how do you think
about the free energy principle as
compared to something like the
principles of natural selection and
evolution how do they relate to each
other which is more fundamental
well i think they're both the same so
that i that's an easy question to answer
so
and even easier for me to answer in the
context of our last exchange about sort
of you know how one free energy
minimizing process is nested within a
slower
higher
temporal and spatial scale
so technically how i literally think
about and how i would sort of articulate
this mathematically is i would
write down evolutionary dynamics
natural selection as a process of what's
called bayesian model selection now
bayesian model selection is just a
a description of what a statistician
would do
if given a particular statistical model
of some empirical experimental data
he or she had to optimize the structure
of that model say delete a particular
parameter from the model or remove
a latent state from from the model or if
you're in say machine learning it would
be uh
add an extra layer to your variation
auto encoder or remove one or switch out
some sort of your
rectified linear function for some
sigmoid functions there's a structural
attributes of anything that can be read
as a model
um
then the process of selecting the right
model is simply to find the model that
has the
the greatest or maximizes the
probability of the data that it is
trying to model that's known as bayesian
model evidence aka or also known as
marginal likelihood
the free energy just is a proxy or an
approximation to that marginal
likelihood the negative marginal
likelihood and indeed in machine
learning it's actually known as an
evidence lower bound so bound
approximation to the model evidence the
evidence that this
these data or the likelihood that these
data could have been generated by this
model
so if you now think about the likelihood
of sensory exchanges in the environment
being a measure of adaptive fitness
what you're effectively saying is
that natural selection is just nature's
bayesia model selection
of the genetic models namely the
phenotypes that have the most likely
exchange that i'm going to find when
sampling a phenotype at random i'm going
to find
this phenotype
characterized by its sensory exchanges
with with this eco niche
so from my perspective uh evolution just
is an instance of
this fundamental imperative to
to maximize
the the marginal likelihood of the thing
as characterized by the states it
occupies all the sensory exchanges if i
was an evolutionary or theoretical
biologist i would call this adaptive
fitness um so negative free energy just
is adaptive fitness when you take a
phenotype and you evaluate the
likelihood of its sensory exchanges over
its lifetime and then if it's good at
what it does
and uh it will persist and it will
persist in virtue of the fat the natural
selection the bayesians the statistician
the you know the
the great statistician comes along and
says yes i like that kind of phenotype
that sort of model because there's more
of them because they persist therefore
they're going to
replicate in the next generation so you
know natural selection uh is is is for
me
a beautiful instance of
the free energy principle in action but
qualified with reference to what we're
just talking about this is you know in
the context of understanding the
coupling between different sort of free
energy minimizing processes you know the
evolutionary process and the phenotypic
or on the ontological process where they
both have to talk to each other and you
know and that's really the interesting
issue is how does the you know the
predictive
phenotype
um
get selected and how does evolution
recognize the the predictive phenotype
in a way that is consistent with the
free energy principle
cool yeah i love that i think that yeah
mike it makes me think of this idea of
the library of mendel um from like
daniel dennett's style book so it's like
oh there's all these different
um dna strands that could exist and then
only a certain subset of those books you
know that library do actually exist
humans and cats and insects and whatever
and so we're kind of choosing a subset
of those organisms or those like dna
sequences that exist but another way to
frame that is it's actually the library
of um bayesian models um you know it's
like it's a library of like generative
models where you're like okay there's a
whole lot of generative models that can
exist in the world but only some of them
are fit with the environment with that
kind of multi-scale goldilocks moment
and so it's like okay we've chosen these
generative models and evolution natural
selection is a way of kind of surfacing
those generative models within that big
old library that actually fit with the
environment such that they can do good
sensory things such that they can repeat
themselves over time um so yeah that
makes sense do you think
that there's a
um you know thinking about other uh
biology and free energy principle stuff
i think that like
i kind of get the brain version of free
energy principle it's like okay humans
and cats blah blah we got these kind of
models of the environment but what about
like at the start of life when you have
the rna soup and you have these like rna
replicators doing their things you know
and then oh replication exists and
that's a huge moment in universal um
time where you have things actually
replicating producing themselves in this
primordial soup
does is the free energy principle at
play there or how is it at play when
like does like the rna have a model of
its environment but it doesn't have a
brain so tell me about that
right um you've been talking to somebody
like mike levin haven't you i i yes yes
yes
so i'll just reiterate what he would oh
no he wouldn't say this because he he's
got a beautiful lexicon uh and he's
fluent in using it but i'm gonna say
what he would say but in maths
so yeah a great yeah a great question um
so i think you know
the principles that we're talking about
is just the principles you know the
existential imperatives and the
principles of things that self-organize
to enable them to persist by returning
to their attracting set so this has to
hold for a thermostat it has to hold for
a single cell organism so let's take the
single cell i think it's a really nice
example it's a particular scale we could
talk about molecules we could go up to
two brains but let's talk about uh a
single cell so
i think it's nice that you introduce the
notion of sort of rna and dna as
basically um nature's specification of
the structure majority model because i
think that's exactly it in fact you can
simulate that quite easily you can just
say well this
this is the prescription
for this phenotypes generative model and
this charity model is apt to fit and
exchange and explore um this particular
eco niche so from a cell i will have a
particular organ i live in or a
particular
medium with the right kinds of nutrients
that i will i will seek out if i am
sufficiently active so the single cell
equipped with if you like at its
beginning um
a
scaffolding a specification of the
structure in terms of its dna
the the most important thing it has to
do is to establish its markov blanket it
has to be able to maintain
um autopoetically
its integrity by maintaining its markov
blanket it's the the surface of the cell
that stops it um
dissolving and dissipating into uh into
its familiar so even all the
electrochemical
uh intracellular processes that are in
response to cell surface receptors and
the expression of active states say the
actin filaments actin filaments of a
cell
which supply with a
motility um that could you know be
mediated just by movements and
morphogenesis or changes in the shape of
the cell or it could be have little
flagella uh you know little little wings
that allow it to uh to move around and
then
that are that that sort of genetic and
epigenetic specification of the
morphology of the markov blanket and how
that markov blanket the surface of the
sensory states are underwritten by
active states which cause the right kind
of movement that maintains the integrity
of the cell these are all just
expressions of um the this
variational principle least action that
just is the the free energy principle
what would that look like well if it was
quite a sophisticated little cell it
would start swimming around where would
it swim to well it would swim to
those
environmental states
that were consistent with the integrity
of its markov blanket that enabled it to
swim so that would look like chemotaxis
it would look as if it was searching out
or at least it was moving when it was um
in you know a concentration um that was
either too high or too low in relation
to its goldilocks its prior prior
preferences encoded by the dna
what would happen if a bunch of these
cells got together well then we move now
to
um multicellular behavior and things get
a little bit more interesting now uh um
you know mike levin tells a lovely story
here because you know there's
something slightly paradoxical about uh
multicellular um
collectives
in the sense that the the surface cells
uh have to sacrifice their ability to
replicate
so it's you know it's almost sort of
anti-evolution but collectively of
course they're made just maintaining
their mark off blanket then it's
persisting in you know in the right kind
of way that evolution likes
but now the what used to be
a markov blanket with its internal
external states is now internal to the
surface of a multicellular structure so
now again we're coming back to this
nesting aspect we've got blankets of
blankets um so blanket building that
your underwrites integrity of a
an organelle or a macromolecule
structure
that then underwrites the integrity of a
cellular markov blanket that then
underwrites the blanket building
capacity of a collection of cells that
ultimately grows into a phenotype and a
creature and possibly even a society and
a species
so at every level you are if you like um
appealing to the same principles but you
can see immediately how something can
sort of
something's behavior
can be evolved or become more and more
sophisticated and much more structured
in its apparent capacity to plan and to
respond adaptively in
very particular ways from a little
thermostat through to something like you
and me or perhaps even beyond through to
our favorite political parties or
countries or
cultures
which we'll get to in a second but yeah
so that i think that makes sense to me
and i think that there's a well hey i
love this idea of like
you know natural selection kind of
choosing it it needs um
markov blankets in order to exist and so
it's like you know those and those
things
those blankets whether it's you know
lipid layers at you know at very early
times or later with like skin cells and
stuff it's like you need the
the thing itself needs to be able to
create that markov blanket in order to
have these internal external states and
so then and those ones like sacrifice
themselves for the good of the whole
organism for the good of the whole so
that makes some sense to me just think
about like the kinds of things that will
naturally evolve on any planet it's like
you'd want you'd expect markov blanks
blankets to evolve wherever um and then
the other piece that you said there was
just interesting it's like yeah these
little kind of you know pre you know
like you know you know uh you know
survival of the fittest chemical
reaction time you know the the very
beginning of of of life yeah it's not
like they have models but they do have
these yeah they have these they have
they have generative models that are not
like our brains and can't do planning
but but i can be in the present and can
follow these chemo taxis so i think i
think that that makes a lot of sense do
you think you know kind of transitioning
now into um
getting closer to humans and brains
we'll kind of you know be in between
full-on memes um and and genes with just
talking about our brains so one way i
think about this is
we have this there's this idea of what
information wants and the kinds of you
know ideas that can replicate from mind
to mind and when they replicate from
mind to mind they have to have a home in
our minds and so something like dun dun
dun um can live within our phonological
loop you know this little piece of our
mind that can kind of like hold audio
signals or whatever um
and you know so much more about the
brain than i do so much more like one
could not even say how much more you
know but how so how do you think about
um
what kinds of information can replicate
to live in our minds like what are the
kind of homes that exist in our minds
and what information would you expect to
replicate and and be stored and be fit
for our brains like if our brain was an
evolutionary niche what information fits
there
right so you've introduced two really
important themes which i know are close
to your heart uh so i'm just gonna
unpack them from my perspective
the first one um
is the difference between um
something like a chemotactic
cell that looks purposeful it's swimming
up the right kinds of concentration
gradients and you when you go on google
or wikipedia trying to save your
knowledge your
curiosity and thirst
for knowledge and find the right kind of
meme uh that's going to populate your
your chapter seven of your book and so
there's there's a
i think there's a fundamental
distinction and as usual
with um when you think about what
distinguishes one kind of thing from
another kind of thing or one natural
kind from another natural kind it's
usually the nature of the implicit
generative model and i say implicit
because you'll never actually know what
goes on the inside because it's behind
the markov blanket but it will look as
if it's behaving as if it has a
generative model
and i think the key distinction between
the sort of the reflexive in the moment
homeostatic behaviors of chemotaptic
cells or perhaps even plants
um and things like you and me
is a temporal depth it's a a depth that
allows the genitive model or put more
simply the generative model has become
sufficiently uh sophisticated that it
entertains the consequences of its own
action or the system's own action i
think it's quite crucial and that brings
two key things to the table first of all
it now has a generative model of the
future
so now we're talking about natural kinds
that can and cannot plan
so you know a thermostat can't plan
whereas you and i can plan and that's
just because our generative models have
acquired a temporal depth that we can
actually roll out and predict what would
happen if i did that and the second
thing of course is the i
did that and suddenly now we have a
generative model
that is all about how
this system how i behave the
consequences of my actions so there now
becomes
an implicit autonomy in the sense of
agency i'm not saying that all systems
autonomous systems know they are agents
but it will they will certainly behave
as if they have a model of their agency
i think that's that's the key thing
and then the second big issue you you
brought to the table here
is you put two of these agents together
how are they going to behave so you're
talking about sort of language and
information well information about what
we started off by saying well
the free energy formulation
puts in a very comfortable position to
talk about information in a meaningful
way and i mean by a meaningful way i
mean information about things not the
information of things so we're moving
away from shannon-esque information
theoretically which is terribly
important you know and
in a sense the free energy principle is
just an information theoretical
principle but i i don't think it's kind
of information that you want to talk
about you're talking about information
about things and we're now in a position
to say well the internal states of
something
now can hold information about something
else it can be very trivial information
could be just some generalized synchrony
as you see with your chemotactic cell or
your thermostat or it could be
information about the future of things
out there the consequences of action
now come back to the question well what
about the universe that has two agents
in it well the things out there now are
the other agent
so now we're in a really interesting
situation so both agents are trying to
minimize their free energy
they're both trying to make their world
as predictable as possible
and they're going to then find a
solution or said evolution will or i
should say evo diva or sort of
evolutionary psychology will find a
solution
that
is a minimum free energy maximum
predictability scenario what does that
mean it mean well it just means that i
am going to engineer my environment to
be as predictable as possible
or i will evolve and be selected if i
can do that
what does that mean if my environment is
constituted by all sorts of other things
like me well it means basically i am
going to
engineer my environment so that we can
all make ourselves as mutually
predictable as possible so we're going
to have a shared narrative and one could
argue um language would be the sort of
the most beautiful example of this or
certainly a semiotics that is shared
between agents so you know
it's a
a wonderfully challenging and
complicated thing to actually
think about particularly to model
when you have predictive processing
systems
that have agency so they're inactive
they're doing active inference
um and they're all trying to predict
each other so now the you know i feel
like the economy almost disappears and
it's just now an ensemble of things that
are trying to persist and persevere
retain themselves in their attracting
states simply by
encouraging this shared narrative so
i i'm using those words because i think
you use the words niche construction and
i would i would submit
that niche construction just is this
slow process
of selecting the kinds of phenotypes
either by
developmental learning or through
natural selection at a transgenerational
level
that underwrite and guarantee a mutual
predictability so anything that helps me
and you converge on the same
generative model of the world
and to broadcast that and to exchange
that actively through some kind of
communication
is going to be in the service of making
sure that my lived world or my at least
my sensed world is as predictable as
possible so
on that view
that shared narrative that generalized
synchrony which has now gone beyond just
a coupling between the uh the the
the total configuration of thermostat
and fluctuations the temperature it's
now much more complicated all about the
future it's all about what are you going
to say next what am i going to say whose
turn is it to talk
now it's your turn
exactly
beautiful um yeah great ending there i
think that there's a i agree with a lot
of what you said which is yeah that once
we get into these
agents that can plan in the future and
that those have a sense of themselves as
an agent that they know that there are
lots of copies of themselves in the
world that they need to be aware of
those copies and so they know what what
their causal loop is connected to like
the stuff in the world i was like oh
that was done by me i'm the one who's
speaking right now once you have all
that then yeah the niche becomes instead
of just like the environment you know if
the sun's niche is the physical laws of
the universe and um the inv and then
like biological niche for like a cat is
like you know the environment a pretty
stable thing now we have this weird
niche where it's kind of um everything
it gets mutual intelligibility and these
other agents and so the niche becomes
this very complicated thing where you
need to have this kind of um yeah this
mutuality there and you're trying to
kind of in this kind of weird game
theoretic evolutionarily stable way
you're trying to coalesce around like
mutual predictability so that that makes
sense to me and and you can see
obviously whether it's being mutually
predictable with language or mutually
predictable with um something like
religion or mutually predictable with um
you know political parties that all is
part of the same kind of idea
let me ask let me let me
rephrase my earlier question actually
though before we get to like religion
and things like that which is do you
think you know getting down to like the
brain level for a second which is
because i agree with all your mutual
predictability stuff but i want to ask a
different kind of question here which is
what if we imagine our brain as as this
little like home for memes and this home
for information
you know one way to imagine is from like
my simplistic perspective which is these
like oh you just like you want sounds
like dun dun dun dun to live in the
phonological loop and so therefore you
know that it'll be inevitable that that
thing emerges and that
catchy songs emerge and can live in our
brains just like it's inevitable that
there would be a fish that could live in
water
but but but that takes a very simplistic
view of a brain and you have a much more
um uh textured view of what brains
actually do
and and what generative models they can
hold and stuff like that so like
what do you think about the kinds of
information that can live
in brains based on the fact that our
brains are these like bayesian brains
i think we've already
talked
about the answer but in a slightly
different context so again it's this
sort of separation of scales
so
the kinds of things that would um
be represented by or constitute the
generative model have exactly the
separation of a hierarchical sort
so that will range
from very very low level very fast very
small scale representations
say of
a visual edge in my visual field in a
very very small part say just say one or
two degrees of visual angle and that
will be replicated throughout
neuronal representations at the back of
my brain and it would just say oh
there's an edge orientated in this
particular direction at that part of
your visual field
very elemental um
very beautifully engineered but still a
very very elemental sort of kind of
information
right up to the very very highest level
usually entailing
um
much
much greater expanses of time
which we've already mentioned in terms
of a sense of self selfhood
so selfhood is just a hypothesis it's
just an explanation
that helps me make sense of my
sensations my sensorium
but it is if you like underwritten by
and informed by all this deep processing
and that by deep i just mean uh
processing undergenerative model that
has a
hierarchical depth so you've got this
notion like of an onion the brain is an
onion with all these sensory signals
impinging on the outside and all the
active states these sort of muscles and
autonomic reflexes affecting
at a very fast time scale what's going
on out there and as you go towards the
center of the audience you know to the
deeper layers of representation the
different kinds information that are
represented are meant to be basically
those that can predict
the unfolding orbits of the layer near
the surface lower down or towards the
censorium so
everything every
concept every construct
certainly that you could articulate but
even those that are so personal you
can't articulate like sort of uh having
the quality of experience or in fact
that's i'm cheating there
qualia is another uh
another uh representation that you as a
hypothesis um but you know from selfhood
through to edge detection uh with your
eyes or hearing a particular frequency
um
there will be a position in this
hierarchical encoding
so when you ask me what kinds of uh
information
can a brain
uh
represent or encode
then they have to be internally
consistent in the sense that the the all
the different hierarchical levels in
this effectively
a realization of inference under
hierarchical genitive model have to be
mutually informing and internally
consistent
and i think looked out like that
then the kind of information
that your brain makes space for
is just the kind of information that
affords a good explanation for your
sensed world
so everything that makes things simpler
and i use the phrase simply deliberately
in the sense of occam's principle
because um
maximizing
your marginal likelihood the evidence
for your model of the world
online in this moment
is the same as
providing very accurate explanations for
your sensations as simply as possible so
this is
the complexity part of
free energy sometimes read as maximum
compressibility or
minimizing the computational cost or
complexity of belief appetiting from our
point of view it just means providing a
unitary
simple parsimonious explanation
so
uh one could contend
that the very hypothesis of self
is one of these
parsimonious
hypotheses that provide a good
explanation for this remarkable
coordination between all my sensory
motor proprioceptive and extraceptive
sensations hang on the simplest thing is
i am a thing and it's me doing all this
moving now not everybody has that and
certainly newborn babies probably don't
have that and certainly lower forms of
life don't um but you and i probably do
i mean i know i do but i'm assuming that
you do i do as well i do
excellent
so yeah any any idea like that that
makes sense of stuff
of the kind that when you first realize
you're having a har mode oh it's just
like that it's it's one of those um
anything that has this sort of
simplifying
uh all all-encompassing
explanatory power that allows you to
explain away all the free energy the
prediction errors lower in your
hierarchical journey model
is a prime candidate for the kind of
information and representation
of things out there because these are
all you know they're all things in the
outside world um
then
i i would submit that's the your that's
the that's the way to think about and
the answer to the question what kind of
information does a brain is a brain
designed to um
to hold and to commit to beautiful yeah
i love that i think
my reflection there is yeah that you
have these hierarchical structure and at
the top level there are these things and
i'm reminded of your the book active
inference and how there's um continuous
signals and continuous generative models
and then discrete kind of uh categorical
general generative models and what you
have to have is for you have to have the
things that are fit for our brain are
things that
that are both fit for the environment
that are sensorium that's like oh here's
an edge detection and that they're also
fit with our like concepts and it has to
be mutually fit so it's like yeah you
have to have both a thing that's i can't
just like make up some random concept
that's not actually fit with the
environment and i also can't make up a
um random like a continuous like stream
of sensorial information that doesn't
have any concept attached to it it needs
both in order to be fit for to our mind
and something like the self or a rock or
whatever is a thing that is actually
what's out there in the world and we
kind of label it as this kind of
categorical thing to it um so that all
makes a lot of sense i have a a question
for you carl which is um is it okay
we're going can we go like 10 like if 10
or 15 minutes over time right now or do
you have uh something else to do
please carry on okay great that'd be
great yeah because i think there's a
couple crucial things that we'd love to
hit um right now that i'd love your
thoughts on so first is let's go to
the um so now we understand the brain um
and we understand genes and we
understand uh the big bang and now we're
going to um this higher level these kind
of nested markov blankets that you were
chatting about before which is
you know this these larger social
structures and kind of society um and so
there's kind of maybe a two-part
question here which is like
how does
you know the free energy principle apply
to these social systems and i know
you're talking about it a bit before
something like mutual um intelligibility
and that kind of like thing but also
maybe like a specific example just like
we use the sun as a specific example
before does something like christianity
um you know christianity is both the
symbol it's the cross it's this kind of
group of people it's this set of ideas
and concepts does something like
christianity
is that like abiding by the free energy
principle does it have a model of its
environment and it's a model of its
environments just like these humans and
the brains and stuff like that so so how
do you think about how the free energy
principle applies to like
social systems
so
very challenging an excellent question
um
so
i wouldn't say that christianity as a
construct
has a generative model
but certainly
um ensemble an ensemble of agents who
are engaging in active inference
should come to behave if they're
sufficiently curious and sophisticated
and um
mathematically empathetic to the the
other members of the ensemble they
should show the sign the kind of
community uh communicative exchange
and behavior which would have all the
hallmarks of something like christianity
you might also
expect that given a sufficiently large
um
sort of cultural landscape that you get
sort of 50 50 splits so you'd expect
sort of to have another kind of religion
which was not christianity and you'd
normally expect there to be about 50 50
splits in a in an evolutionary stable um
steady state sense
um and there are good and principled
reasons for this
and even if they're not easy to intuit
mathematically you can easily
demonstrate this using numerical
analysis or multi-agent games the the
the the emergence of this is is very
interesting um and it comes back to
something we mentioned before um
about the difference between um animate
objects that have this sort of reflexive
aspect uh and the very very simple
um
versus
sentient creatures like you and me with
a sense of agency and these deep
generative models that free us from the
moment because we we can imagine the
consequences of our action
in imagining the consequences of our own
action we have to now
plan
what we're going to do we have to have
um a notion and narrative so it's no
longer just oh i'm going to swim in that
direction or this direction or i'm going
to switch the radiator or off because
the temperature has dropped it's much
much more
a much more deeply temporal structured
navigation of the world with narratives
but narratives
have to be chosen so we're talking about
planning as inferencing we're talking
about creatures that can plan and
ensembles creatures that can plan
if they plan
they have to have the ability to score
the goodness of one plan or the likeness
of one plan relative to the other and it
turns out
that mathematically
those plans whose outcomes or
consequences
have the smallest expected free energy
are those that have the greatest
information gain
what does that mean well it means that
anything that has a deep generative
model that exists
must therefore behave as a curious
creature
now if you're a curious creature you've
got a problem because you now have to
select the kind of data that's going to
resolve your uncertainty so you have to
be able to estimate
what kind of data what kind of exchange
for example is going to have the
greatest expected information game which
is an important part of the expected
free energy
so you now get into this very difficult
situation which we all contend with
which is who do we listen to
what news channels
do we listen to what papers do we read
what social media do we commit to which
church do you attend on sundays
these are all choices we make that
contextualize and have a profound effect
on the sensory evidence for our genitive
models
and so when you put this into the mix
then the obvious thing of course is that
for those things that are sufficient
like me um and
i have direct exposure to then we're all
going to converge on the same constructs
the same narrative the same uh
cultural commitments in terms of the
language we use the social norms the way
that we uh make things easier for
ourselves in terms of making things
predictable with deontic cues and signs
gestures um
you know in language um you know
you can see evidence that much of our
communication is just basically pointers
to
you know
you're like me i'm like you so uh you
know let's start our engagement
uh however in so doing
then if there's somebody in another
group who is
now infers ah well that's not my group
but i'm i'm in this group they are going
to
select those policies
that they think are going to have the
greatest information again resolve their
curiosity and make everything um
internally predictable so they can learn
their environment but it's not going to
be the same as yours and usually the
only stable strategy
is you've got a 50 50 split because if
one's too small it's not getting it's
absorbed into the big one
so the only stable one is is
christianity versus not christianity or
brexit versus not brexit or trump versus
biden wherever you look
you know these sort of cultural
commitments that enable you to seek out
the kind of information that reassures
you yes you know this is the kind of
thing that you are um
will uh will inevitably involve some
segregation so now you you actually got
another instance of blanket building now
you've got a segregation which is a
completely functional
and necessary part of self-organization
you know it's autophagys self-assembly
defined operationally by constructing
building blankets and preserving them
to isolate to segregate um in a
in a way that defines not only you as an
individual but your uh kin your culture
your species uh your place in in in this
world
that's going to um
you know be a vince in this instance at
the level of
cultural or social norms so another
beautiful example of the on the same
kind of blanket building principles this
auto police's self-assembly in chemistry
this would be self-assembly in cellular
biology it would be waterprooesis um i'm
sure there's a good word for it in in
cultural psych evolutionary psychology
you you do you know what the word is
what is the tendency to segregate yeah i
mean it's a good question i i'm thinking
about there's like yeah group that's a
good question i know of um i don't know
actually what that would be called um
you know group identities um identity
construction something like that is is
are the things
yeah
i'm not sure yeah yeah but we'll i'll
google it and get back to you
but yeah it's that it's that same like
you said it's just like you know no
matter what um the universe uh needs it
it evolves towards blanket building and
this is just another form of blanket
building is the tendency to segregate
and and as you say it's like yeah and
the crucial part of it is that you want
things that
as we move through our lives to um yeah
to have things that are are are stable
and are clear and that the information
that we're getting is is not all crazy
all the time but it's like stuff that we
know and then we feel safe with so that
that makes a lot of sense to me and i
think i mostly agree with you on
christianity not having a um a model of
and it obviously doesn't have a
generative model in the same way that we
do but there's something about
christianity in that
it knows
how brains work it it has evolved to be
this thing that does know
because if it didn't then it would it
would die out and so there is some sense
that has a generative model do you kind
of see what i'm saying no sorry yes
you're absolutely right in in that sense
in the same sense that we that me as a
phenotype is a you know i am an
embodiment of the generative models
of my eco niche you're absolutely right
and i think christianity as a construct
is exactly that kind of thing
what i meant was it may not have a deep
judging model it doesn't plan
um so as with many things that get big
they that they don't plan quite so much
anymore uh like the sun doesn't which is
you know or the
um the you know
a cosmological scale you lose the
ability to plan so
it's a it's a similar issue a question
you know does
does natural selection plan
uh and i think it would be difficult to
argue
in the sense that you and i plan that
natural selection plans but certainly
natural selection i'm sure i'm
absolutely sure that you're right
in relation to sort of um
things like christianity um
that you'll have a well-defined markov
blanket then they certainly have a
generative model i'm just saying it may
not be a temporary deep generative model
no i agree with that i think i think
there's an interesting it makes me think
of um
and this is this world of memes and
thinking about how there's some memes
that have a super
that um like virals that just spread
very quickly and so this is
like some kind of hip new thing but then
i will say
that evolutionarily there is something
about something like christianity
it doesn't have it it can't plan but it
does a workaround for planning which is
that it it gets access to long-term
energy so it gets um lots of bequests to
the church so that it can get more money
or something like a corporation that has
like you know apple has a really big
balance sheet and has a lot of money um
kind of like how the sun has lots of
access to energy so it can perpetuate
for billions of years or whatever so too
do these like longer term i agree that
doesn't have the ability to plan but it
has something within it that allows it
to retain for longer such that when new
information comes in it like doesn't
just it doesn't just go away like a
viral does yes so
um let's go let's move to our fight ago
well no i'll just say i mean but you've
just you you i think you've beautifully
articulated that you know
the existential imperative just to
persist you know it's last man standing
and of course you also say it has to
have the right context in which the last
man can stand uh you know so it has to
have that as how that resource it has
has the sun without the sun there might
not be any christianity because there
might not be any others
exactly exactly um and that can take the
form of uh you could be last man
standing by knowing what's going to
happen in the future or you can be last
man standing by just having a reserve so
that weird things happen in the future
you're like ready for it and you're kind
of your meme or your replicator can kind
of work through the new environmental
niche that exists um so moving to our
final question here um and and thank you
again carl for the bonus time
so talking about so we've we've gone
from genes to memes and now we're in
this weird new reality where we got
computers and um you could call them you
know susan blackmore calls it like the
new third replicator and you know she
calls them dreams i like to call them
keems like these computer memes um
and so there's there's something weird
here about this new kind of thing that's
emerging and a lot of folks are worried
about ai safety and how this thing is
kind of maybe optimized for some things
for different values than what we're
optimized for and and that we might just
kind of you know get turned into paper
clips or whatever so how
and i know that the free energy
principle has a lot of overlap and
you've kind of discussed some of it with
machine learning and things like
minimizing the elbow and minimizing kind
of loss functions and stuff like that
how so so i guess there's a two-part
question here one of which is like how
does the free energy principle apply
with machines and ai having kind of
generative models of the world and then
maybe the second question
connected to that is like how then does
that
um what does that imply for ai safety
and like how we should be making sure
that its generative models are ones that
include us and that like don't want us
to die or whatever
right
um
so
i i think that the you know sort of
certainly the active imprints
instantiation the free energy principle
has a lot to say about artificial
intelligence and generalize artificial
intelligence um
in a way that moves us beyond
reinforcement learning applications or
deep rl applications
and i think
what it has to offer is exactly uh what
we've been talking about in terms of
this artificial curiosity so if you
haven't had him on yet then yoga schmidt
hoover would be the man to
wax lyrical about about the importance
of sort of
creativity fun and curiosity which is a
you know this sort of information gain
uh novelty seeking uh aspect of um
expected free energy minimization
so
what we're looking at
in terms of the next generation of
computer artifacts or edge computing or
robots are basically curious robots
what does that mean well it means that
you'll now have intelligent data mining
because part of curiosity
is knowing where to look
so you know i suspect there's going to
be a
this is probably rubbish
i'm talking rubbish until about five or
ten years have passed but i'll say it
anyway my guess is that in the next five
to ten years
big data is going to die
and what will be replaced with it will
be replaced with
tiny sparse
salium data so it'll be all about the
quality of the data mining searching out
the right kind of data that has the
greatest information gain that's going
to resolve the uncertainty that this
data miner this robot or this or this
user so that's going to be i think
a
a change in the future
which of course if you want to bring in
sort of climate change issues and the
amount of energy we currently spend on
on computing is quite uh
is quite an important argument from the
point of view of sustainability but i
think mathematically that's what you're
active in for the free active inference
and the free energy principle uh brings
to the table and it also relates this
minimum complexity maximum compression
argument that the the most likely
artifacts including computers that will
exist in the next decade or so are those
that are most efficient and have the
most simple way of providing accurate
predictions in the simplest way possible
so they will be cheap they will run on
batteries you won't need generators to
do your uh to do your uh to do your date
of mind because you'll you'll know where
to look
um
what the
in terms of sort of you know the the
paperclip um issue
i think that
that inherits from um a behaviorism um
and a commitment to reinforcement
learning and value function
um formulations of optimal behavior
that kind of formulation doesn't exist
in the free energy principle you know
there is no
value function or reward function
all there are
are
preferences about the outcomes of
behavior
and those preferences are just the kinds
of things that are you are most likely
to
encounter or produce as a consequence of
your behavior
and
as such
um if you
produce an outcome that makes somebody
cross
like making too many paper clips or
accidentally starting world war three
then you're not gonna see that you're
only gonna do that once and it's not
gonna be the kind of thing you prefer
producing what i'm trying to say here is
that
built into the normative account
ascension behavior
is a
safeguard against the the paper clip
manufacturing
automaton
because it's a whole point is to make
its world as predictable as possible so
it knows what the likely outcomes are
because it can predict what those
outcomes are and those outcomes as we've
said about four times now are deeply
contextualized by the environment and
the eco niche in which this agent is
operating
so what that means from my point of view
is that it's more likely that the next
generation of artificial intelligence
will take its lead from um automated
pets and carers so you know
the things that that are going to sell
that are going to be bought off the
shelf and therefore fund research and
incentivize people applying the next
level of machine learning which
one might submit would be active
inference
are going to be um sort of curious
artificial pets
sort of series that are really
interested in how you're feeling they're
curious about you and they're gonna ask
you because they want to know about you
because it's your that you're their
world
so this is a much more benign picture i
think where there's where you actually
have um
a co-evolution of artificial and natural
uh intelligence um in the same way that
we have a co-evolution with our with our
pets then we have a coevolution with our
agriculture and with with our technology
um so i i don't think that i can't
imagine
provided that the free energy principle
is an apt description of our planetary
evolution i can't imagine um you know
things the singularity that you you see
popularized in science fiction and some
of the popular science literature
yeah beautiful yeah i think that there's
um so two pieces there one is yeah i
love the idea and i agree with it to
some extent which is like right now
we're just doing brute force just like
you know give the gpt3 just like 70
billion parameters and 96 layers of the
transformer just let it roll you know
and actually and even even transformers
this new kind of artificial intelligence
architecture it does this kind of what
to look at thing it has this like list
of like what you know when you're
looking at text it has a um an indicator
for where in the past it's looking and
the layers kind of tell it where in the
past to look to understand to predict
the next um kind of uh word and the
sentence or whatever and so it's it's
our we're already starting to do this
kind of look only at specific things in
the past and then like you say i also
agree with like
and we're already exploring this it's
like we've done the big data thing but
of like oh just more data equals better
models and actually what they're finding
now is there's this new one where they
all they asked it was to they um instead
of like a 70 billion parameter model
like at gbt3 it was like i think a seven
billion parameter model that
outperformed it but what it did is it
they asked it hey ex like explain your
reasoning as you're doing it um and it
got it for some reason that just made it
so much better and so i just i just
think that you are probably
directionally correct and from a free
energy
principle perspective it's like finding
out the kinds of information game the
kinds of feeds just like we have our own
kind of feeds to that we consume from
what feeds will it be doing and not just
all of them but specific ones um to to
go for so i agree with that and then on
the side of
the ai alignment yeah i think i mostly
agree with that i think that there's a
um
and there's this kind of like
co-evolutionary perspective that i think
a lot of the ai safety people don't take
into account they're just like oh no
value function and the value function
gets optimized for and we're all going
to die it's like okay wait there is this
co-evolutionary domesticated
relationship where we domesticate each
other we're both trying to mutually
co-understand each other and mutually
come to this like shared world where we
both exist as like agents in this world
and i think the hope would be you know
when they do bad things um that we are
that's not a fast enough takeoff
scenario such that when they do the bad
thing we say bad and then their gender
model changes that they're like okay i
won't do that again and we hope that
when they do it bad the first time it's
not it doesn't like ruin everything but
just like only has a small impact so
with that said thank you so much carl
for the the convo today i think i
learned a lot and hopefully the
listeners learned a lot um as a note
where should people i mean hey check out
i just read carl's carl is a prolific
extremely prolific which is really cool
um check out my recommendation i'll add
these in the show notes i'll add some
kind of like um things that will help
you you know so like this amazing
15-minute video that carl did about
getting you into free energy principle
i'll also link to the new book about
active inference if you want like a
deeper dive especially around how brains
do it in the kind of a more formal kind
of mathematical sense and bayesian sense
um carl do you have anything else to
that where our listeners should go or
any other things you'd like to tell them
thank you for the opportunity but no i
think i think you did a grand job of
everything that will be useful thank you
very much
beautiful um well with that listeners
thank you so much for coming um and
goodbye everybody bye carl
thanks so much for listening today
if you like the show please give us a 5
star podcast review or subscribe on
youtube
and if you'd like to chat about this
episode with a community of amazing
smart ambitious divergent people come on
by and join our discord you can find it
at root.co that's r-o-o-t-e
dot co
and then finally if you'd like to
contribute to these ideas being shared
more widely in society you can support
the podcast production team at
patreon.comreeselandmark that's
patreon.com
r-h-y-s-l-i-n-d-m-a-r-k
thanks and see you here for the next
episode bye